Hello and welcome back to
another video with ItsDrDan.
And today we're gonna be learning about
calorimetry, meaning that what this is
is this is used to measure heat changes
in both physical and chemical changes.
So what this, what this utilizes is
generally we try to try to figure out
how much heat is being absorbed or
released during a chemical reaction.
It's very common in your chemistry
course where you might have to use a
coffee cup calorimeter, like the one
I drew here, where essentially on the
inside you'll have all kinds of different
chemicals, maybe mixed together,
maybe chemicals mixed with water.
Maybe you'll, uh, drop something
into it and see how much
heat is being transferred.
And it gives a, for a very cheap
method, it actually gives very
accurate results in determining a lot
of the information about a reaction.
Especially if we want to figure out, let's
say if it's exothermic or endothermic.
Now the coffee cup calorimetry
is a really cheap way, but
it does give decent results.
Now, why do we care about calorimetry?
Well, it's mainly for everybody that's
interested in nutrition out there
and trying to figure out exactly
where's the calories on the labels
of our different foods come from.
Generally, there's a very more
sophisticated version of it, like a bomb
calorimeter, uh, which is the name of it,
where they actually essentially kind of
make your, your food sort of explode and
burn it to figure out how much energy is
stored within the chemical bonds there.
So how much chemical energy
they're being stored.
So essentially they'll use, um, uh,
try to, we have all these different
conversions here that are very useful.
Write 'em down.
Um.
We're essentially one cal.
So big C is equal to 1000
calories with a little.
So I try to color code that they
are different from each other.
There's big and little, um, being
that welcome to the imperial system.
And then one large C calorie is equal
to one kilo cal and 4.184 joules,
which is essentially based on water
is equal to one calorie little c.
Or 4.184 kilojoules is
equal to one calorie big C.
So now when it comes to all these
different energies, we can break them
down in like the different food types.
So like carbs, fats, and proteins, which
are major macromolecules that we ingest.
You can see like fats have
the most energy within them.
So this is the reasons why it takes
a, you know, it's good to have fats
for energy consumption, but it takes
a lot to break them down and happens.
You get a lot of energy, but
usually they're stored for later.
Things like proteins are usually,
you know, it's better for developing
muscle and carbs are quick burning.
So they all have their own
different types of values to them.
So what we're gonna be doing
in this particular video is
looking at the different ways we.
As a calorimeter, which will go
off a lot of it lab based examples.
is what specific heat all about.
So we're gonna be looking at
the specific heat capacity.
Now, what that is just as a reminder,
is the amount of heat that is required.
Increase the temperature by one degree.
So this is for every gram of substance.
So when we are using this, right, it's, I
call this the MCAT equation because I like
to think of all the pre-meds out there
that need to use this, where essentially
we have heat, which is joules, and this
is equal to our mass, which is in grams
times specific heat, which has its own
kind of special unit of joules over grams.
By Celsius all together, that's not a
formula, it's, it's the derived unit
for it, multiplied by the change in
temperature, which is TF minus TI.
So final minus initial, and that's
in degrees Celsius right Now this can
also be used for as calories as well.
So you could have calories
over grams by Celsius two.
Um, just keep in mind, the
heat would be calories.
Now when this is happening, keep
in mind, energy must be conserved.
So this is all about seeing how
the system and the surroundings
are interacting with one another.
So for all these problems, the system
is our chemical reaction in this case.
And then our surroundings is it's,
it's the solution that is being
here, that is being used here.
Okay?
So like water, for example, is
considered to be the solution.
Usually, a lot of times when you see
the letters like AQ written next to a,
um, a chemical compound that's letting
you know, Hey, this is made in water.
The surroundings of the water,
of the, the surroundings in this
case is water or your solution.
Um, system.
A system in this case.
So it again writes the chemical reaction.
Now, why do we care about that?
Well, remember, energy is
conserved, meaning it's
transferred from one to the other.
So if all the molecules are reacting,
they're kind of all bonding together,
breaking apart, doing their thing, well,
all that energy it has to get transferred.
The surroundings, and that's
what we're gonna be measuring
with a thermometer in this case.
So instead of using system surroundings,
we're gonna redefine that to
say, oh, reaction and solution.
And being that it is conserved,
we can set this term equal to zero
and kind of also rearrange it a
little bit for our own purposes.
So if I kind of like we take this
guy down here and copy and paste
it being that it's equal to zero,
we can actually move things around.
And say, Hey, this is gonna be equal to
where one of these is the negative value
equal to the positive of the other one.
So keep in mind that the signs will
be opposite of one another, and this
is what's gonna allow you to tell
something It's, exo, or endothermic.
So what we're gonna be looking
at is whatever the sign is of the
reaction tells you Endo versus exo.
So the sign being positive
for endo, for exo.
So depending on if the temperature
goes up or down, we'll actually
have an effect on that.
Alright, let's take a look at some
of the different problems and how
we can actually solve for these one.
So if I have the following, it says 10
milliliters of sodium hydroxide with
a density of one point 21 grams per
milliliter is mixed with 40 mls of water,
the density of one gram per milliliter.
Your initial temperature of the
solution is 17.2 degrees Celsius.
And it is raised to 57.1 degrees Celsius.
Assume a specific heat of 4.184
joules per grams per Celsius.
Calculate the Q.
Oh, that's a lot.
How do you do that?
All right.
The first thing is what we're gonna do
is we're gonna highlight our values.
So we have 10 mls of sodium hydroxide
with its density, and then you also
have 40 mls of water with its density.
Now, why do we care about these two?
Well, in order to use the MCAT equation,
so one thing that I didn't mention
before is the mass portion of it.
The M is the total mass of
everything mixed together.
So total mass of solution, meaning
it's the small portion and the big
portion, all of it added together.
So all the things you mix together, so.
With being, especially when
they're the same phase.
So they're both liquids.
We're gonna add them together,
we're gonna add them together.
Alright, what else do
we have in the problem?
We also have two temperatures.
We have 17.2 degrees Celsius, and
we also have 57.1 degrees Celsius,
and then the specific heat.
So let's kind of write down
all these things that we got.
Let's start with the masses.
So we had 10 milliliters.
Of sodium hydroxide and we need to
convert that to rams for ourselves.
So 10 milligram, 10 uh, milliliters.
We're gonna use the density that was
defined earlier and that's going to
convert that to value so our units cancel.
And what we will get from
there is we're gonna get, um,
12.1 rams of sodium hydroxide.
And then we're going to add that to
the mass of water, which as you can
see from earlier, we had 40 mls of
water, and it has a density of one.
So that's a one-to-one ratio there.
So 40 grams of water is equal
to 40 milliliters of water.
So let's add that up.
So 12.1 grams plus 40.0 grams of water.
And we're gonna have a
total mass of 52.1 grams.
So now what we're gonna be doing is, is
essentially taking our mass, Timesing
it by our C and our Delta T value.
So we have our Q of our
surroundings, our Q of our solution.
It's equal to the mass,
which is 52.1 grams.
We're gonna times that by C.
which is 4.184.
Joules over grams by Celsius.
And then we're gonna multiply
that by the change in temperature.
So our temperature was 57.1 as a final
temperature, and 17.2 as an initial.
So Delta T is equal to final, so
we'll write that down for ourselves.
So we had a 57.1 minus 17.2 degrees C.
All right, so now is that all
of our piece of information?
It looks like it.
So we're gonna take all of that together,
multiply everything and what we're going
to get after multiplying 52.1 times
4.184 times parentheses, 57.1 minus 17.2.
We're gonna get 8697.7, which we are going
to round to three significant figures.
In order to, to de to show that
properly, we're gonna have to put
that in scientific notation or put
it as kilojoules, one or the other.
Okay.
So this would be your answer
for this portion of the problem.
Now I have a follow-up version of
essentially, well, what is the Q of the
reaction and what exactly does that mean?
Well, the one above here
was the Q of the solution.
So meaning that if we think a system
and surroundings well, this part on
the inside of the box reaction, what
you have outside is your solution.
So how exactly do those two equal?
Well, remember you of the reaction is
equal to what if one of them is negative,
the other one's positive with a solution.
So being that.
We have for one value is 8,000,
70 point times 10 to next third,
it's gonna be the opposite sign.
So our Q of reaction is going to be
negative 8,000 or 8,700 Joules or
8.70 kilojoules, meaning that this
is gonna be an exothermic reaction.
Okay?
So that's what that sign means.
Is that it tells you whether or not it's
exothermic or endothermic for its final,
so they're opposites of one Another.
First part was positive.
The second part is negative because
they're equal, but opposite signs.
Remember, energy must be conserved, so.
This is one problem that we can see.
Let's take a look at if we want
to transfer heat from, let's
say a hot object to water.
Alright, so let's break down another
word problem, which is a very common
common lab example that you may have seen
or will see in introductory chemistry.
The one thing that we can commonly
do is we can see how heat transfers
from one object to another.
Meaning that if we assume a closed system
where essentially any energy that's stored
within the system can be transferred
to the older object, we can actually
find out a lot of the information here.
So one thing we have with
this heat transfer problem
is essentially what is it?
So let's go through it.
And I made it a long
one kind of on purpose.
So you can kind of see how, how,
how it is that we break this down.
So step by step, you find an unknown piece
of metal sitting in a drawer at home.
You decide you want to apply what you
learned in chemistry class identity.
Okay?
So what you do is you heat up
the piece of metal to an initial
temperature about 102.3 degrees.
Okay?
So this is for the metal is
what this information is for.
You know, I'm gonna color
code this to be red for metal.
Now what it says next, you
measure out 50 grams of water
with an initial temperature.
Of 20.1 degrees.
Okay, so these are both for the
actual block, for the water itself.
So now it says you carefully drop the
hot piece of metal into the water.
Okay.
So what do you think is gonna
happen if that, if that occurs?
So if you were to drop something very hot
to water, it's gonna cool down, right?
It's going to transfer
that heat to the water.
So it's kind of, think of that
stereotypical blacksmith scene
where you see like scheme and
all kinds of stuff coming up.
It's sort of like that.
Now when that happens, the heat
is transferred and what it's gonna
do, it's gonna, both of them are
gonna reach a final temperature
at twenty-six 0.3 degrees.
So they're both gonna get to
the same final temperature.
Okay?
So we have all kinds of little piece
of information that we are kind of
getting here that we want to kinda
label and to see how can we do
this and understand what we have.
Okay.
Now once essentially it cools down,
you measure the mass of your metal and
you determine it's 19 grams on the dot.
Now it says water has a specific heat of
4.18, four joules per grams by Celsius.
Find the specific heat and determine
its identity, and it lists a bunch of
little specific heats over here in the
corner for us to figure out what we
think it could be based on how it looks.
So we drop that in and
we wanna figure it out.
Now, how do we do that?
Well, the first thing is,
is remembering system.
The negative of the system is equal to
the surrounding, meaning that the negative
heat of the metal is equal to the heat of
water, should be perfectly transferred.
Now what can we do from there?
Well, both these are cues, meaning
that they're both MCAT equation.
So what we're gonna actually do is we're
gonna plug in the MCAT equation for both
of 'em, let them equal to each other.
So what are we trying to solve
for is we are looking for the sea
of the metal, which is over here.
So what we're gonna do is we're gonna
simply do a little bit of algebra for
ourselves and move some things around.
So what we'll do is we'll divide
both sides by the variables we
know, which is essentially the, um,
temperature of the metal, right?
You know, that value.
So we'll copy that on both sides.
We'll divide, divide it.
We also know our mass
of the metal as well.
'cause we read that
earlier in the problem.
So now when that happens, it all cancels
out on left hand side as a result.
So this goes away and this goes away.
And it gives us a new equation that
we can essentially use as like a
plug-and-play equation for ourselves.
Solve for the specific heat of the metal.
Okay, so this will be
see of our metal here.
So let's take all of the values that
we had from earlier and plug them in.
So now that we have our C of the
metal, that's gonna be equal to our
mass of water, so which was 50 grams.
We'll times that by the
specific heat of water, which
is 4.184 joules grams, Celsius.
Multiply that by the
final minus the initial.
Which the final value was about 26.3
degrees for both of 'em, 26.3 degrees,
and that's minus 20.1, I believe.
But this is what's going in the top of the
denominator of the new of the numerator.
And on the bottom is the mass of
the metal, which was 19 grams.
And while you're doing this, you want to
be really organized as much as possible.
Negative symbol out front and its
final te, its initial temperature
was 102.3 degrees C and it
also reached 26.3 degrees C.
So once we plug in all this into
our calculator, what we'll do is
we'll multiply the tops of 50 times
4.18, four times 26.3 minus 20.1,
and divide all that by negative
19.1, uh, or sorry, 19.0 times 26.3.
Minus 1 0 2 0.3, and what you're gonna
see is this is gonna make a negative
value over here in the temperatures,
and it's gonna cancel out the negative
on the bar, um, when that happens.
Okay?
So when we plug all these value
in, we are gonna get about
0.898 Joules over grams by C.
Now, how do we get those values?
Well, if we kinda look
really, really closely.
Essentially the Celsius will cancel
out over here and the grams are
gonna cancel out on the left.
So the only thing that's gonna
be left is the C units all the
way over here on the far side.
So our specific heat of
our metal is about 0.898.
So let's look, let's see if, see
if we can match it to something.
And what we're gonna see is that our
aluminum, which is about 8.9 or 0.897.
Is really close.
So being that these are intrinsic
properties or intensive properties
are bar made of aluminum, and this is
how you can do this kind of problem.
So if you have to work up an ear
lab data or try to understand little
things in class, this is one of
the harder problems that you have.
So generally, these aren't usually seen
on introductory general chemistry exams,
but in homework and in labs, it's more
common being that you have more time.
For general chemistry one, this is a
problem that could easily be for an
exam that level's a little bit harder.
So try to make sure, you
know, just setting those MCAT
equations equal to each other.
All right.
Thank you so much for listening.
I'll bye now.